no the Lions stance very well you can
record it okay you can put your phone up
here
oh sure that's okay we're gonna freeze
the people in front so make sure you
have a sweater this system the people in
the back are hot and the people in the
front are called
so if you're not recording please turn
off your phone
and we'll do a nice slow lion stance we
probably take a break in the middle okay
some people weren't here during the long
room so I'll do some explanation as we
go
okay please blow your nose here's a
tissue if anyone needs clear your throat
please don't clear your throat during
the meditation okay let's go
[Music]
so the lions dance meditation starts
with a tracking some noise in the room
air conditioner or heater refrigerator
traffic noise outside kids noise or
small noises in the room if you're in a
diamond mountain cottage you can use
them and it's too quiet you can use the
sound of the air hitting your eardrums
sounds like static on a radio glue your
mind to that some
if you'd like to meditate for about half
an hour 40 minutes you can do 10 breaths
at each step if you'd like to meditate
for an hour you can do about 20 breaths
you
then the lions dance the first eight
levels are all about comparing the
previous level to the next level and
always seeking to go quieter and it's
also a kind of gotcha meaning that you
drop the louder level and you go to the
quieter level and there's a very active
comparison of the two so you put your
mind on the air-conditioner noise and
then you consider the first form room
level which were using the heartbeat and
compared to the noise of the air
conditioner in the heartbeat is quieter
this is called shiitake number Chen in
the study of meditation and by
comparison of a louder place to a
quieter place we consciously choose the
quieter place and we move into it so
compared to the air conditioner which it
represents the desire realm the gross
physical world we live in we choose the
quiet place of the heartbeat so moved
now to the heartbeat follow the
heartbeat first form Rome level
which is not really the forum realm but
if you focused only on your heartbeat
for as your meditation as a pretty
devoted meditation during your lifetime
then you would be reborn into the forum
realm
first form realm which is very very
similar to the superheroes in the movies
you see like Wonder Woman Thor or
spider-man and then after that karma
wears out after that debit card is used
up you always ninety-nine percent of
those people go to the lower realms so
we don't want to devote our whole
meditation just to quiet we want to
reach some kind of content which works
against our tendency to see things as
coming from their own Sun but to get
there we go through the steps of getting
quieter and quieter like moving up an
elevator eight floors but don't get out
in the first eight floors don't devote
your life to meditating on just quiet it
doesn't stop the process of aging or
death
so heartbeat first formal
you
then if your mind goes back to the
air-conditioner sound of the fan
just use it as a step focus on it glue
your mind to it and then step back up to
the first formula with your heart beat
so in this meditation system
distractions can be used to climb to the
next level second forum level we try to
imagine that rather than watching the
heart from the outside we enter the
heartbeat in technical terms that's
moving from vitarka and vichara to
deeper level so quiet to to a level
deeper than that so imagine that you're
inside the heart like a small room and
it's beating around you maybe you are
even beating with the heart beam go
inside the heart because it's a more
quiet place than watching the heart from
the outside each time we're going more
quiet
you
third form round level
classically we drop any emotional
feeling of attachment or pleasure with
the meditation posture and object we get
some emotional distance from the object
so I like to imagine the heart is now
beating a little bit ahead of me like a
little bit far away and it's it's
beating in a vacuum and I don't relate
to it much it's beating by itself a
little bit far away and the sense of me
is much less here almost cancel so
imagine the heart beating in a vacuum
especially emotional vacuum you don't
connect to it you don't relate to it
it's just beating it's a deeper quiet
than being inside the heart
fourth formula
is characterized by a high state of
single pointedness and we pretty much
dropped the entire sensation of the body
particularly the pleasant feeling of
good posture in meditation so it's
almost as if your body has been
anesthetized
and you can't feel it anymore and the
mind
sharpens like a laser into a single
point as it helps classically in
meditation to reach a state a single
point if you're having trouble reaching
a single point then think of something
tiny and put your mind on that and that
helps a lot to focus the concentration
so we use a grain of sugar at the fourth
form room a single grain of sugar
floating in darkness white crystal
beautiful and moved the mind inside it
and dropped the feeling under body
completely
these are not antidotes to sansara these
will not solve your problems of life
neither with your family or your job or
the bigger problems of mortality but we
are climbing up a ladder to a place
where we will deal with those problems
you
now I go to the first formless room
level if you only meditated on this for
long periods during your life you would
be reborn in a place where there's no
growth suffering you don't even have a
gross physical body and you would live
like that for many years and then when
you died you and always go to the lower
realms because you would use up your
karma so we don't stay in this
meditation we'll just use it to move up
it's called cell JAMA in Tibetan so cell
JAMA means now we show flexibility in
meditation can we go from a single grain
sugar to a state of mind which expands
to the whole expanse of space itself so
we imagine a huge lake and our mind is
like the surface of the lake and it's on
a horizontal plane it spreads left and
right especially and we're going to drop
a small pebble in the center of the lake
and ripples will go out to the left and
the right I like to make it one ripple
for me it's less than an inch high like
a centimeter
I have found that it helps a lot if it's
completely silent the movement of the
ripple left and right is completely
silent this is more quiet and deeper
focus than the grain of sugar but we are
showing off our mental flexibility we
can go from a single point to the
expanse of the whole universe and still
get quieter
okay drop the pebble
and see the ripple and don't let it stop
if you lose focus bring your mind back
to the ripple and keep seeing it move
out out out
no in no short
you
then come back to the center of your
mind I for me it's like dark and it's a
point in the middle of a room about you
know two meters off the ground and come
to the center of your mind and we go to
a more quiet place called the second
formless realm level and namche attire
and we're gonna imagine turning on a
light and the light flies from the bulb
in a sphere ever expanding wider and
wider
and that light is not white or yellow
it's clear light and again it's not the
real meaning of clearing lighter muscle
in Buddhism but it's just like a crystal
color which is not the meaning of clear
light and Buddhism then but we imagine a
crystal light expanding from a single
point in a ball and I'd like to make it
as big as the earth and then I'd like to
see it go beyond the Sun and reach to
the stars beyond the stars
the universe has countless planets
somewhere right now there are people
meditating like us in many places
countless places
they are meditating on the second
formless around oh I like to imagine my
sphere crystal light is overlapping
their sphere of Crystal Light somehow we
are touching each other maybe one day
we'll be aware of it so when I say go
turn on that light and let the crystal
light expand endlessly in all directions
like a ball and that light is your
awareness your own mind
okay go turn on the light don't let it
stop keep pushing it further further at
the same time try to be more quiet
inside than the leg
you
third formless realm the seventh m-28 of
us
counting their air conditioner is zero
this is called Chi young male and we
just try to imagine that we turn the
mind off like a switch no thoughts no
feelings no awareness Oh just dark black
as if your mind died and so when I say
go
just shut the mind off if thoughts come
feelings memories push them away keep
the mind turned our deeper quiet then
the expanding mind of the second
formless realm okay go ahead turn off to
mine
you
for formless realm level and the highest
of the eight meditations we use to
prepare our mind for actual meditations
so these eight are not real meditation
they are just stretching the mind
warming up the mind for the meditation
these are not meditation they cannot
help your life in a real way at the
fourth formless realm level we still the
mind is turned off but when thoughts
come memories feelings we just
surrendered to them we let them move
through the mind we don't make the noise
of trying to stop them as we did with
the last level so it's a more quiet
place extremely quiet place where we
just surrender we tried to turn the mind
off but if it doesn't turn off we just
let it go we staying in total silence
okay let's go
you
track 3 deep exhales don't open your
eyes yet
then you can gently open your eyes take
a stretch microphone any questions about
that part that's the first part of the
meditation we're gonna start the second
part in a few minutes but anybody have
any questions about first part Thank You
geisha I had a question during the
instructions when we're moving from one
form to the next when you're giving the
instruction do we stay in the form prior
to my mind was jumping back and forth
yeah it's a good question
Janice's question is when I'm giving the
instruction should you start moving yet
or should you wait the reason I'm giving
instructions is that you can learn the
meditation and when you do it by
yourself for a week or something use the
recording follow the recording and then
after that you can stop using the
recording and then you just move up to
the next you decide and it's always a
process of comparison okay
share talking number 10 you check the
level you're on you say that's quiet but
I could go quieter and then you kind of
look ahead to the next level you know
and you say oh that would be more quiet
and there's supposed to be a emotional
feeling of going deeper and for me it
feels like drilling down okay so you
know that you get quiet then you get
used to that quiet and then you say
let's see if I can go more quiet
and you drill down so actually listening
to a recording you can't get past the
desire but you're just imagining okay so
I think it's important to say you have
to practice a lot to really get to a
formless around meditation or you know
I'm describing them
you're imagining them but when the real
thing comes you'll see it's much deeper
okay so there's no noise there's no Sun
so you have to practice it's like
playing a soccer or learning a language
it takes time and you have to practice
every day okay even if you can't we just
did it like an hour even if you can't do
an hour every day you can go through the
levels faster okay you got to go to work
then push it a little harder five
breaths each level okay when I say five
breaths in the beginning count five
breaths then move later that becomes a
distraction okay so but you'll get used
to the timing there's a five breath
version twenty minutes there's a ten
breath version about half an hour and
forty minutes there's a twenty breath
version it's about an hour okay and so
first at first use your breath to count
when to move on okay but later you have
to drop that because that's also noisy
okay okay other questions
thank you a lot for your teaching book
during the meditation so when I tend to
think about things instead of getting
down it's more agitation all the time
and this especially in the first aid
level it's it tends to make our mind not
to think so it's kind of against my
tendency and I got pretty frustrated
when I like during the peaceful lake and
some projects so every time many times
when I finished this meditation that
have you tired because I was like trying
so hard to put it back and it's not so
peaceful it's because my mind is just
tend to think about things analyze
things so how would you suggest I do
that
yeah good at the beginning I mean your
mind is very active human mind is very
active Stanley it's more active like
mine and so to get the mind to listen to
you is struggle a lot of in the
meditation books who wrote the best
meditation button kamila Sheila how many
he wrote three books gum in Tibetan
they're called gum room in Sanskrit
they're called bumming a Croma okay
and we read them together in the first
two comma Sheila's there's nothing in
those books that you don't find in the
Long Room the Long Room comes from those
books okay so in in those books they say
it's very common for a person to go to
the lama and say after you taught my
meditation after you taught me
meditation my mind got worse
yes my mind used to be quiet sometimes
now when I meditate it's like very noisy
it's worse than before
and then the Bhavana chroma the gum room
the meditation manual says your mind was
always terrible you just didn't know
okay
now you're listening to your terrible
mind it sounds worse okay so the more
you practice there's a stage first six
months when you feel frustrated you feel
like my mind's getting worse you're just
learning to listen to your mind for the
first time it is that bad it always was
that bad but you never noticed it
because you were in it and you didn't
learn to watch it so being in the mind
being in your thoughts and learning to
watch your mind us are different okay
your whole life you've been in your
thoughts
busy busy busy talking talking talking
now you start to watch it and you say
gosh now my mind's getting worse okay
actually you're just learning to watch
your mind after that you learn to
control your mind okay and make it more
quiet so there's a stage where it's
exhausting you're fighting the mind
actively my suggestion is just so you
don't get discouraged go up quickly
through the eight and go to number nine
okay like the purpose of going through
the aid is to build up your meditation
muscle okay I like to say your mind is
you know your mind is like a dog like a
bad dog and you have the dog on the
leash right we have a small dog we
babysit sometimes me and Vee it's a very
active little black dog and he wants to
go go go go he will pull you he's this
big he will pull they tell you
and then you have to grab the dog you
know the dog wants to think about lunch
in my case it's always lunch or maybe
you have something else you'd like to
think about your last fight with your
husband or what somebody said about you
on the internet and then the mind wants
to go over there you know so you have to
say no no come on come on come back come
back then he gets quiet for a while
like our little black dog then he's like
then he thinks there's something else
and he goes then you have to pull him
back you know and then every time you
pull it back this muscle gets stronger
this is meditation muscle so in Buddhism
struggling is a good thing okay
giving up is a bad thing struggling is
exhausting if the bad dog is called my
mind okay it's exhausting okay just
anybody who did a three-year between
Thelma did two-three retreats in a row
you can she can tell you it's a struggle
you know people came into my retreat
cottage after my sphere retreat I
remember the first day when I came out
and they came in for the first time in
three years they saw my inside of my
cottage you know and they said oh gosh
la it looks so peaceful
I say yeah like Vietnam was peaceful
many war fought in this cabin many many
many ways you don't expect meditation to
be like you know if you do it wrong
maybe it's peaceful I don't know but if
you're really watching your mind it's a
struggle and it doesn't happen the first
day that you feel peaceful it's not
gonna happen like that somebody want to
turn off their alarm
you have to fight you have to struggle
okay and every moment that you struggle
with your mind you are making progress
okay and if you spaced out called Ching
hua tumble spaced out oh I'm in the void
everything's nice I'd not think about
anything there's a name for that it's
called a subtle dullness and it's a bad
bad meditation habit if you meditate
longer than you have capacity you will
definitely go there okay most people
when they meditate should start with 12
minutes okay
that's an old tradition in Buddhism 12
then maybe you can go to 20 minutes okay
but if you try to sit there for two
hours definitely you you will go to
Chinua tamil shyama means spaced out
okay just don't mine okay
not sharp not clean what does real
meditation feel like I like to say when
you're watching a good movie okay what's
it called guardians of the universe
and you're like watching the movie you
know and in the beginning everyone's
eating popcorn and the green lady is
beating up people and the big guys
saving her
the handsome guys running around and the
little tree guys helping and the Fox or
something yeah then you're like eating
popcorn and they are fighting and then
you're waiting for this special moment
when the green lady kisses the handsome
guy so everybody know for two hours
everybody's like eating popcorn you know
in an American movie you know and then
suddenly they start to go like this and
then everybody popcorn goes like this
and everyone's like this maybe he's
gonna kiss her now after two movies
finally you know and they're going
closer and closer you know and
everybody's like they forgot the popcorn
this is focus okay that moment in the
movie whole 200-300 people like this
okay
so the feeling in a good movie that's
meditation that's what you want it's not
like that okay really 99% of people who
meditate are like this okay
a real meditation mind is sharp clean
happy engaged excited oh this is coming
Jesus coming okay like that okay if you
like that then you you are actually
making a bad habit okay you're hurting
your mind and you're hurting your future
okay so don't meditate too long meditate
20 minutes take a break like we're doing
right now then go back okay when you get
stronger then then do more but don't do
it too much at the beginning okay you
waste your time and you make a bad habit
it's very hard to change later okay okay
any other question
you okay go it's not for me actually
yeah yeah this is from a min Reza poor
from Vancouver hmm he asked my question
is sometimes when I meditate I see
things and feel things that are very
scary or they perceive them as scary
they may not be real but they scare me
so much that I have to take a break is
this normal and how should I deal with
this
yeah okay good
so DCI level three is about meditation
how to meditate a CI three also is
meditation and the big breakthrough that
tsongkhapa made the the way he explained
meditation the huge huge breakthrough
that tsongkhapa made is in a letter that
he wrote to a student of his name know
and Appa and he also wrote him what the
three principal paths right and but he
wrote another letter to know on Dhamma
and he said meditation is seeds opening
in your mind okay and every time you
hear your thoughts all day sees they're
opening in your mind so we're gonna do
that next in this meditation little
thoughts are coming out of seeds in your
mind and actually you are not the
thinker you are the listener okay so
when you hear thoughts in your mind all
day you are just the witness okay you
are not the talker why the talker left a
moment ago the talk is not here anymore
okay I like to say it's like light
coming from a star okay the light of the
stars you saw last night unbelievable
beautiful last night because it's just
after the new moon and the light left a
year ago or ten years ago hundred years
ago then the light is coming to you by
the time the light reaches your eye that
star can be gone already already died
down your thoughts are the same by the
time you hear them the talker is gone
okay so you cannot control the talker in
your mind
it's not possible okay people used to
come to my llama you know I was
translator I told you I translate his
English into English people say repete I
feel depression all the time I feel
depression yeah I say Rinpoche they feel
sad he says okay I got it
then then he said okay I have advice for
you you know sometimes they came from
far away to ask my mama question he say
you should be happy then he started
doing his mantra again you know that
means interview is finished you know
they're not me and the other person are
waiting then he's like you're still here
I said Rinpoche they have serious
problem maybe you're gonna commit
suicide they have depression he said I
told you what to do once be happy then
I'm like then the person go away they
are angry and depressed then I go
upstairs they're ribbity right why why
you say be happy why you giving some
help he said it's too late the seed is
planted already seed is opening they are
listening to a star that's already
finished you think it's too late - you
are gonna be depressed today okay if you
don't want to be depressed next week
then be nice to other people that's all
plant some good seeds this week next
week the thought you hear in your mind
when the seeds open will be nice thought
okay got it meditation is the same okay
you cannot meditate you cannot control
your mind you will hear what comes out
of the seeds maybe you will hear
something quiet
or maybe you will hear something noisy
but by the time you hear it it's too
late
Gwen Kerr said you cannot push a tree
back into the ground the guy who
invented Vipassana I took his course
when I was twenty you he said you cannot
push a tree back in the ground
it's not possible okay so the real key
to meditation is not to disturb other
people make other people happy make
other people peaceful be nice to other
people next week
the seed that open in your mind will be
peaceful but you cannot control your
mind it's not possible because the light
already left the star by the time you
hear it it's too late got it
the real key to meditation is not to
disturb other people's mind be be nice
to other people's mind make them happy
okay
make them peaceful next week your mind
will be peaceful
okay got it I forgot what the question
was oh yeah so if you feel nervous or
scared if strange images come in your
mind while you're meditating those were
planted last week it's too late to stop
them it's like telling the light from
the staff to the light from the star
reach you it's like talking to the star
100 years ago it's too late you see so
you have to deal with the seeds in your
mind learn the four powers for cleaning
away bad seeds and be careful not to
make other people scared or nervous okay
and and then those thoughts won't come
during meditation if they're coming it's
a sign that you're being mean to surface
okay and you have to stop again okay all
right let's do the second problem a
little pallet we'll get to you later
okay all right here we go
second part of the meditation blow your
nose do your Yancey stuff turn off your
phone
this is the second part of the Lyons
meditation okay lion stance then we'll
take a pee-pee break okay
so you can meditate on your bladder if
you want okay we won't spend too long
so we just pretend we just came out of
the fourth formless realm we turned off
the mind and when thoughts came we we
didn't confront them now we start the
real meditation the ninth floor is the
real meditation the first eight floors
including zero floor the air conditioner
noise are not meditation they do not
contradict the way the normal mind sees
the world so now bring to mind one of
your teachers in your life it could be
your mother or your father who are your
first grade teachers it could be a
school teacher it could be a lot of us
had sports teachers that we felt close
to it could be a spiritual teacher like
a priest or a rabbi or among a lot of us
were taught or our occupation by someone
that person taught you law you can think
about a historical teacher like Buddha
Jesus Moses Mohammed
your heart teacher is especially good
someone that you feel has helped you in
your life more than anyone else we call
a heart teacher and for some of us if we
haven't met someone yet that we have
this feeling about them this is my heart
teacher then you can imagine your
perfect heart teacher and you can bring
this teacher to sit with you in
meditation right now this is the
beginning of level 9 and I encourage you
to make the teacher real it's not a
picture it's not imagination it's not a
statue it's a breathing warm living
teacher sitting with you knee to knee
your eyes are closed their eyes are open
and they're looking at you with great
love great emotion very happy that you
are meditating
then there are many qualities about your
personal teacher that you admire and of
course there are many qualities about
them that we would like to develop
ourselves and that's why there are
teacher so in this meditation level 9
you choose just one of those qualities
that you love about this person in your
life could even be your child I had a
person who said his root Lama was his
dog and I believed him
so think about one good quality that you
admire in this teacher you can change
the teacher every day if you want in the
meditation or you can stay with one
teacher for four or five days and then
change to another one as you do this
meditation more and more you will find
more and more sweet qualities in this
teacher it's not very useful to isolate
a negative quality in another person and
meditate on it it doesn't uplift your
mind it doesn't make you a better person
I encourage you to choose a admirable
quality in someone else and focus on
that so choose a quality
now go back to the middle of your mind
which is where we've been meditating for
me I imagine a dark room and in the
middle of the room imagine a small nest
like a bird's nest and inside that nest
are six or seven beautiful beautiful
eggs silver color as if there's a
spotlight on them and they are very
bright shining beautiful and now imagine
that one of those eggs is cracked open
split and an image comes out
luminous image small maybe the size of a
marble and it comes out of the scene and
like a hologram and it's the image of
your teachers quality in my case let's
say I'm thinking about my llamas
consideration of other people and so I
imagine a silver egg cracking open in
the centre of my mind and out comes an
image of consideration and it in my
meditation and it moves towards the
front of my head and it moves out of my
head
and it settles on my llamas in front of
me like a coat and it covers them and
this is why I see the consideration of
Manama if it's more comfortable you can
imagine the seats coming out of your
heart if you tend to get nervous in
meditation you can imagine them seeds
coming out of a place near your spine in
front of your spine at the level of your
navel and that will ground you and the
most important thing at this stage in
the meditation is this feeling that what
you see in your teacher the beautiful
quality in my case consideration is
actually coming from seeds in my mind
they are making pictures
those pictures are settling over myeloma
and the goodness that I see in my lama
is coming from those seeds think about
it then go back to the second egg watch
it crack open watch the image come out
watch it settle on your normal and
that's the second moment of
consideration then go back to the silver
eggs and repeat this process for a few
minutes
in real life it's happening at a rate of
65 eggs opening
one after one per second
we're slowing it down
if you do this part correctly you should
have a sort of a shocking feeling that
what I see the beauty I see in my
teacher is coming from me I may not see
that quality in myself but I have the
seeds to see it in in another person
you
now we take a fun trip
we try to imagine what did I do to plant
those seeds so I must have done
something if I see something in my world
if I see a quality in my teacher it has
to be that I planted those seeds so it
could have been in this life but we're
going to pretend that we can go back
into our past life and try to imagine
something you did in a past life to
plant those seeds and be creative be
happy it was some beautiful things you
did in your past life some really nice
habit you had for many years how you
treated other people and be imaginative
let go don't limit yourself use any
image that comes to your mind because
all of those are your seeds they belong
to you any story you can make up about
your past life is coming from your seeds
it may not be correct it may not be
exactly what happened someday in the
future you will be able to see your past
lives directly but right now let's make
a story let's write a movie about your
past life when what era was that a
hundred years ago was it a thousand
years ago was I in China was I in India
was I in Europe was I a Native American
and how did I treat people what was I
doing day-to-day that I planted these
seeds to see such a considerate llama
okay so write your story just a few
breaths then we'll take a break
you
now come back here llama
in front of you now you have a better
feeling for why you see this quality
respectfully ask them to move to the
side and now imagine another image of
your Lama that looks just like the first
Lama but this is like the second husband
in the kitchen
this second imaginary Lama they're good
quality is not coming from me it's not
coming from my seeds I don't deserve it
it's not from doing nice things to other
people it's just an accident
I met this Lama by accident they don't
come from me there's no history between
us in the past there's no past lives
when I planted them or met them there's
no future between us like a grand
beautiful ending to this story and
there's no future lives together there's
no future lives
there's no personalized we're not going
to enlightenment together it's just an
accident
I met them by accident I came here by
they came here by accident if you follow
this train of thinking everything's
random I meet people by accident there's
no past reasons for this even the
universe itself came from a random
explosion called the Big Bang and little
dust particles hit each other billions
and billions of times and finally they
bang together and made my nose made my
llamas nose made my llamas eyes made
this world and it's all just a big
coincidence accident I like to call this
llama this accidental llama I like to
call them boo-boo llama random llama
BIGBANG
and try to feel a sense of for me it's
almost like outrage like this is wrong
my beautiful exquisite dear Lama is not
a Big Bang accident it's not true that
we have no future together no happy
ending we have spent many lifetimes
together they're coming from these
beautiful seeds I object to this idea of
an accidental Lama I don't believe it
and then wipe away this fake Lama
accidental momma bring back the real one
and be aware that the place where the
real nama is sitting
is where the fake llama was wiped away
from and that's emptiness okay without
emptiness I can't see this llama coming
from seeds so practice the feeling that
you're nama living sweet llama exists in
the space left behind when we cancel the
accidental um that's your llama living
in emptiness
you
track three long exhales
and then open your eyes take a stretch
I'll answer questions about that after
the break okay so we're gonna take a
break 15 minutes I believe there are
some delicious green drinks and fresh
juices for you in the kitchen I
encourage you to drink a green drink on
my in my opinion green drink is just
below yoga I hate both of them but if
you drink one you'll be able to have a
good class okay
so just hold your nose and drink the
green drink okay see you in 15 minutes
okay all right so we're gonna go back to
the verse at the end of the diamond
cutter Sutra we have about an hour and
towards the end of the hour we'll go
over the schedule for your meditation
for today okay
please say Taraka Tamira depo my Avishai
boot buddham sharanam cha they did Abram
cha even Josh Tavia Sanskrit um okay
we're Antartica which means star we said
there would be six different meanings
I'm gonna review the first three that we
covered first one is shared by a
combination of master Camila Sheila
master buss Abunda Tony nama and John
Young Shia and that's that stars can
only shine in the darkness and the
darkness in their understanding
represents that we don't understand the
object okay and then the star here
represents things that bad things in our
life okay because we don't understand
and then if we did understand they would
go away as if the Sun came up okay
and we use the example of your husband
or your wife somebody object when I say
husband they said wife also cause
trouble so when you come home you know
you yelled at your kids last week then
you come home and your husband yells at
you for no reason
calls you stupid okay and then you have
two choices you can understand that they
are coming from the sea little silver
eggs
your mind like the llama or you can
think that if I didn't do anything and
they are just hurting me
okay if you think you didn't do anything
before
that's like darkness and then the
husband will be like a star and and they
will hurt you okay then a buddhist
person of course we should try to change
our seats the nice thing is you don't
have to tell your husband that you're
changing him you just change your seats
there's no need for long discussions
fighting etc okay you can change them
that all but that doesn't mean you
should let someone hurt you or abuse you
okay that's not Buddhist either okay so
if someone's hurting you you know you
you don't have to just stand there and
let them hurt you
and say it's my seat okay you can take
action if you have to leave or you have
to seek advice or you have to seek even
legal means then of course you should do
what you have to do but understand that
whether it works or not depends on your
seats okay so there shouldn't be anger
there should be no anger I'm responsible
but I choose to leave or I choose to
seek some help legal help or other kinds
of help psychological help that's fine
here we have a very strict policy at
Diamond Mountain you sign it every time
you come here no alcohol no drugs no
weapons no hurting other people no
harassing other people physically
sexually any other kind it's a policy
here for 14 years we have a process if
if you have something happen to you and
you want to report it talk to one of the
board members would you stand up board
member
Rahm Scott me John Michael Stanley jig
me okay Melissa and Melissa if you have
a problem with somebody just report it
to one of those board members if you're
shy you can write a email to us and it
can be anonymous okay you don't have to
tell us who you are and we have a system
for for investigating problems here okay
and that system is 14 years old I've
been at all the board meetings I think
during that time we have investigated
people we have issued warnings we have
what you call discipline people we have
even reported people to the police so if
you feel you need if you have a problem
here just feel free to to tell somebody
okay and if you have an old problem that
you're had you can still tell us okay um
but the stars coming from here okay that
doesn't mean you don't tell the police
so you don't tell the board okay but it
means that you don't get angry because
you understand where it's coming from
okay and you can fix it by fixing your
seats okay all right that's the first
one second one $10 and I said no no the
stars are the truth of suffering okay
and when the Sun comes out which is the
direct perception emptiness those stars
cannot show themselves okay
a person who is seeing emptiness
directly especially cannot have
suffering and they will they can
actually never again collect Karma for
suffering
they can still get old karma ripening
but they don't make new karma for
rebirth okay like that then coin
September due May said I have another
understanding its that emptiness allows
things to appear okay so for him the
darkness is not ignorant the darkness is
emptiness we just did a meditation where
we cancelled the boo-boo Lama accidental
uhm we cancelled them like a white movie
screen okay that's emptiness cancel the
accidental Lama that gives room for the
real Lama to come from the projector
called your mind
okay got it okay so according to Quentin
bit do me the darkness is actually
emptiness and it allows things to appear
like stars so for him everything is
appearing because emptiness allows it
you can just think of a white movie
screen is emptiness and then your mind
is the projector and what images you put
in your mind will be projected onto the
emptiness okay if there was no emptiness
there would be no things okay if there's
no black space the stars have no place
to come okay that's the third idea now
we're ready for the fourth one so coin
Jacques Demy do me the same Lama says
therefore the darkness in the first
example in the diamond cutter Sutra can
be exist or not exist on well let's say
good thing or bad thing
the darkness good thing or bad thing was
misunderstandings a good thing yeah good
okay he said you can think of the
darkness as a good thing or a bad thing
okay when we talk about misunderstanding
the darkness is a bad thing okay and
then the star is your husband the second
husband okay but you can also think that
darkness is is a useful thing called
emptiness it's the white scream and
without it we can't have anything okay
all right so that's the fourth way to
understand the star and the darkness he
says you know you can think the darkness
is a bad thing or you can think that
darkness is a good thing okay and that
if you want to go deeper
that's the emptiness of darkness that's
the emptiness of darkness Neil Young
sounds good to some people and sounds
terrible to other people the darkness
can be misunderstanding
or the darkness can be emptiness which
allows other things to appear also good
things
okay got it that's understanding number
four okay
understanding number five comes from a
dude an aria named Nagarjuna okay the
gardener so famous sometimes he's called
the second Buddha and the first one of
the first great artists okay and after
we finished Kamala Sheila we're gonna
start his most famous book which is
called wisdom
okay sometimes then of course people
gave it a longer name
he likes short names okay Mulla progeny
a part of meat carica route text versus
unwisdom
but he called his book pres new wisdom
okay 27 chapters all in poetry extremely
beautiful and it's like taking a trip to
the Buddha realms okay so we're gonna
study his most famous book all teachings
on emptiness in China Tibet India Nepal
Mongolia Japan they all come from the
Gaggia okay so from that book so you're
gonna have a good time okay I think it
will take 2-3 years okay we will go
through the port I have never seen a
good translation of it okay all right so
anyway the Gardner wrote many poems but
he also wrote commentaries to other
works and there's a famous prayer called
Samantabhadra okay samantabhadra's
prayer in samantabhadra's prayer
the most typical offering do you guys
know
do you remember yeah is to imagine the
sky covered with flowers and offered to
your teacher it's part of the llama
Champa and the Georgia both okay so he
wrote a commentary on that famous prayer
and in there he talked about how the
stars appear in a glass of water okay if
you go out at night and diamond mountain
and you chopped oh let's not talk about
chopped Oh
if one person under you have a bucket of
water okay and you can see the stars
reflection in the bucket of water okay
so he says the gardener says the stars
meaning is illusion okay
that's the meaning of the star is just
illusion okay because you can see a star
in the bucket of water but it's not real
it's not the real star okay you use sky
guide app on your cell phone and you
point it at the bucket of water and
nothing will happen
seriously by the way if you don't have
that app it's awesome sky guide app you
can point it at the stars here and it
will give you the name and the history
of the star
okay okay so that's number five the
gardener said the star represents
illusion because you can see all the
stars in a bucket of water okay number
six it's just common sense
I put in some common sense once okay
stars don't last they change every 12
hours or so okay they go away so you can
say the sixth meaning of the star is
that they are impermanent okay they
always go away one of the most famous
questions about this verse in history is
is he talking about impermanence or is
he talking about illusion because some
of the nine metaphors they seem clearly
to talk about impermanence but then some
of them seem to clearly talk about
illusion
okay and there's a huge question for two
thousand years
you know it's Buddha talking about
impermanence or is he talking about
illusion how would you vote on this one
huh you like that I vote for both I
agree okay I'm sorry
right yeah it's both stars come and go
every morning they disappear just like
on relationships
just like our money just like our life
just like our body they come they go
okay but also they are illusion okay and
that illusion depends on the darkness of
not understanding okay so now you're
ready to appreciate meditation number 20
okay we're starting at the end okay
meditation number 20 the nature of the
things around us how many examples how
things are three I mean there's gonna
the first three are about you know
what's the world like okay the first
three of the nine examples describe the
world okay our world so so far we've
covered one of the 23 meditations and we
covered one-third of it okay so maybe
you should stay here for a few months
the nature of things around us stars of
the black night now we're going to go to
the second one
what's the Sanskrit Tamira Tamira say
Tamira three roots here okay three
separate roots here Tim Tom Tim there's
three sanskrit roots
okay three meanings of this sanskrit tem
one is darkness okay
in paris key cut Nazified
John John NIDA Timna chimney chimney oh
yeah you see the route in Russian you
don't see it in this darkness route in
Russian TEM dark okay so it means
blindness it came to mean blindness you
can't see it's dark okay
the second route is tongue means to be
cut off to be cut off yeah and a place
in a village which was separated from
the rest of the village for worship was
called tongue bow okay temple comes from
that got it
same route it means cut off what do you
call a particle which is cannot be
divided up Tom Adam okay so that's the
root to cut okay there's a third meaning
of tongue which means afraid afraid
timid comes from that temerity comes
from done okay so get this feeling the
second example
Tamara Tamara means I'm alone I'm cut
off
I'm blind and I'm scared okay
I'm cut off I'm blind and I'm scared
this is Tamara okay
and it means in this case a cataract on
the eye okay a extra skin on the eye all
right it makes you blind makes you turn
okay
now I'm gonna give you six meanings okay
six different meanings for the cataract
okay six different meanings for this
covering on your eye
Camela Sheila Vasa bamboo Tony Lamar
Johnny on Shiva say the main meaning is
that you think something's there which
is not there because of this bump on
your eye you see something out there
which is not out there it's just a bump
on your own arm
okay it's just a problem with your own
eye okay the second husband okay looks
like he's out there but it's really a
problem with you okay all right got it
that's the most famous interpretation of
the Kim Yuna the cataract okay hmm
they always divide it into two kinds
okay meaning number one is always
divided into two kinds you see people
and you see things which are not there
okay
you see people and you see things which
are not there
the husband is people but like traffic
okay you get in a traffic jam someone
called me they said I'm gonna be late
coming from Tucson I said why they said
traffic jam I said traffic jam from
Tucson to brief you can tell me in
Shanghai or in Berlin but come on
traffic jam and buoy
give me another excuse next time okay
who whoever it was alright but traffic
jam is also coming from you okay don't
blame the traffic don't get mad at the
traffic okay the purpose of studying the
diamond cutter Sutra is to stop getting
upset at things okay it's you it's a
bump on your own eye okay
don't get upset at people and don't get
upset at things okay they're coming from
you okay all right mmm second meaning
this is $10 rumba he likes to talk about
the truth of suffering right sometimes I
like to call it the fact of suffering
because it refers to the suffering
itself okay all right so you can say the
four facts okay so he says only if you
have a defective instrument of
perception
can you see suffering in your life okay
got it he relates to I problem to
suffering truth of suffering okay and in
Aria a person who's looking at emptiness
directly they cannot perceive suffering
not possible so for him the bump on the
eye is suffering truth or suffering
okay second meaning and if you didn't
have the bump on your eye you couldn't
see suffering okay
Aria doesn't see any suffering while
they're seeing emptiness okay all right
third one quaint short-tempered do me he
says let's talk about chandrakirti let's
go back to the entering the middle way
okay very very famous book on emptiness
entering the middle way okay what's the
middle way in chandrakirti's entering
the middle way who can tell me
it's ngoz newest book
okay so chandrakirti's book is the most
famous book recently on emptiness okay
twelve hundred years ago and sorry
fourteen hundred years ago and it
it's called entering the middle my
mother macaw Vitara but the middle way
here refers to the book called wisdom
okay so that's a nickname for
nagarjuna's book is the middle way okay
in his book he said elaborate May long
Tasha Lauren on daytime my in nature day
jung-min okay
and he's talking about a famous example
from ancient times for things you see
that are coming from you and the example
is like when Geshe Michael takes a
shower in your bathroom Scott can see he
always leaves like 30 or 40 hairs on the
white porcelain you can see hairs you
know if I don't clean it up you can see
okay
then John de Quixote says but some
people have a scratch on their eye then
they see lots of hairs and they're
cleaning them but they're not hairs it's
a scratch on your own eye okay so here
we see in the third meaning of the eye
problem you will see what you have the
seeds to see you will see the problems
that you have the seeds to see and
that's the first law of karma what's the
first law of karma huh chiquan Mexico ok
banana makes banana watermelon next
watermelon
what the bump on your eye makes you see
will match what you've been doing
recently
Gani you see a hair on the porcelain
it's because there's a long fine scratch
on your own eye okay and you see a
yelling husband it's because you yell at
your kids last week the scratch on your
own I will match what you see you see
they mean the content of the illusion is
coming from how you treated people last
week or last month
okay got it the kind of bump on your eye
will decide what you see you see you you
hurt somebody you yell at somebody then
next week the the hair you see in the
bathroom which is actually your own eye
scratch okay
will match what you did last week that's
the first law of karma
so for quench attempt it do me this is
the important thing when you talk about
a defect of the eye scratch on the eye
you will see the same thing that matches
how you behaved last week okay okay
there's no random it's always much what
you did last week if you told your kids
last week how beautiful they are what
would your husband say when you walk in
the door you're so beautiful okay got it
is that a scratch on your eye yes good
answer good answer
all right meaning number four this is
important for coin show than they do me
it's called confirmation confirmation
confirmation okay it means what happens
if a person without a scratch on their
eye comes in the room okay what happens
if a person with clear eyes comes in the
same room okay you came in the room you
know you open the door and your husband
said you're stupid okay for no reason at
all that evening you call me I didn't do
anything okay got it then your friend
comes in who just got back from Camilla
Sheila for okay they come in the room
and you say can you believe this guy
call me stupid
your friend will say who I don't see
anybody yes right there my husband just
call me stupid what I can't see anything
I didn't do anything well where is he
he's he hiding
no he's standing right there I don't see
anything okay got it
someone who understands the diamond
cutter Sutra walk in the kitchen right
after you they say I don't see any
husband who I didn't do anything husband
okay got it
someone with it without the scratch on
there I come in the same kitchen look at
the same place they don't see her
husband who I didn't do anything
got it okay that's called confirmation
that's important to enjoy them be to me
fourth meaning of the scratch if a
person standing next to you doesn't have
a scratch on their eye they'll say no
Geshe Michael cleaned all the hairs out
there's no Harrison there that's just
your eye okay that's a problem with your
eye okay
that's called confirmation that you are
crazy okay non crazy person come in the
room with you say I don't see any house
I don't see any husband who's
not my fault this is the story of every
interview I ever had with a student okay
hundreds of times every year I talked to
people you know people telling me we had
a problem nobody listened to you come on
every year I talked to hundreds and
hundreds of people okay
I'm gonna buy a tape recorder put it in
my pocket it's gonna say maybe you
should try to force dance maybe it's
coming from you okay I I can say I've
talked to thousands of people okay
and they the stories are almost all the
same my husband baba baba I know about
the first steps of my husband's
different I said tell me about your
husband and then I don't have this karma
I don't even know their husband right so
I don't have a scratch on my eye and
that's why they come to me because I
have other scratches with my own
relationships but I don't have the same
scratch you have so yeah I can give you
advice this is called confirmation non
crazy person talk to crazy person when I
go to my Lama for advice I'm the crazy
person there the non crazy person and
they don't have a scratch you see they
can say uh I don't know your your your
husband seems like a nice guy to me no
no no well maybe it's a scratch on your
eye I understand that's true of other
people but not in my case okay that's
called confirmation how many we got for
the cataract for good let's go to
numberphile Vasa bond Oh master buss
Abunda okay he says think about the
Wheel of Life okay
by the way how do you prepare to think
about the Wheel of Life lions dance
that's why the lions dance was taught
Dana sang in Nanjing painting ends and
onions you pay tangent Belgium looked
him down do me to October J Maitreya use
the lion stance go straight to the Wheel
of Life
that's the coolest that's the coolest
thing okay will of life in our case
we're watching the seeds come out for
the llama this is dependent this is
dependent okay
now generally in the rule of life
everything is messed up everything in
the Wheel of Life the twelve parts of
the way of life is suffering okay that
wheel is about the causes of death and
the wheel is held in the arms of death
okay so this is an important thing to
master vas a bundle he says if your
equipment of experience your eyes your
ears your nose your mind if they were
created by karma then they are defective
okay that's very interesting your
telescope has a scratch on it
your telescope called your eyes your
ears your nose
we're built with a scratch on them okay
a normal person cannot see hear smell
taste feel or think of anything without
making a mistake okay it's the nature of
your equipment you were born with a
scratches on your eye okay and it's
important to understand them okay
the natural human condition is to
misperceive everything all the time okay
it's only with massive dosages of the
perfection of wisdom that we can ever
see anything correctly because we were
defective from the factory okay called
your mom's womb you came out with
defective equipment why it was produced
by defective thoughts okay your nose
your eyes your ears were produced by
ignorance okay
the blind man a normal person who
doesn't have training has to see the
wrong thing okay if they just use their
eyes okay so that's a very deep Buddhist
thing it's not just a mistake in your
thinking your equipment is broken okay
you can't see anything without feeling
that it's coming this way
okay normal human condition you come out
of your mom five years later you know
you see something you believe it's
coming this way that's built into your
eye also okay same with Lama chipper
cookies okay they taste like the sugar
is in the cookie but the sugar is not in
the cooking the sugar coming from you
the sweetness coming from you okay but
your tongue will lie to you because your
tongue was born from ignorance your
tongue was born defective okay the
tongue thinks oh this cookie sweet
it's not true sweet doesn't exist in the
cookie sweet coming from you got in your
equipments broken that's master of us
abundant number understanding number
five okay all right now the good news
number six okay it's not all bad news
number six
Salo Buddha WA lo budva NIC has to learn
this Adam has to learn this okay say G
se lo boardwalk
Nick Nick low boudoir Nick Nick
okay nickname means it's part of your
mind which cannot be removed it's like a
cancer that's so spread in your body if
they cut it you will die you know you go
to the doctor you say he says you've got
cancer and you say can you cut it out he
says it already metastasized it already
metastasized we would have to cut your
entire body out it's too late okay it's
spread everywhere okay it's part of your
body now cannot be removed okay that's
called nickname okay say nickname
it means metastasize cataract cannot cut
it out without destroying the eye okay
not possible okay lobola means it's on
the front of the eye and if you have a
good surgeon you can remove it you can
cut it off which one is ignorance the
second one low budva that's the good
news
okay that's understanding number six
okay
understanding number six is the cataract
is not part of you it's removable okay
it's removable all right
it didn't miss Costas sighs yeah okay
you could still remove it skillful study
skillful meditation skillful teaching
skillful men effort on your side we can
cut it off okay and you will see things
correct me got it
okay those are the six understandings
let's go on to people
okay long I deep deep
besides it's deeper okay
the full form is deep pass a s before
another word becomes oh okay but that
the word is deeper okay in a in a verse
it has to change the PO deep oh okay the
role word is deeper okay okay this route
is easy
the route is deep or D and it means to
shine to shine okay
PV and B are interchangeable in
linguistics so what comes from deep
divine okay debbye okay a lot of god's
names in the old days gods were sky gods
okay so jove comes from the Jupiter
comes from that Jupiter means Jupiter
and the ancient form is do do Peter okay
do you Peter
father of the light do you bitter and
then you became geo became Jupiter so
Jupiter means Jupiter father of the sky
and many dairy names are like that Zeus
is like that this comes from do you
Tuesday comes from that it's the day of
the god name - TIFF - okay which means
the sky gone okay the bright bright gone
okay so Deva divine deity day Zeus
Jupiter Tuesday Jove they all come from
the same root okay do you do
okay so deep means a shining lamp okay
now master Kamla Sheila by the way how
many meanings here
let's do
six okay first one is master vos Evander
master Kamla Sheila China epidural
j-johnny Lama they say the same thing
they say to to make a butter lamp like
here okay you need two things you need
the the wick the piece of cloth and then
you need one you need the oil or the
butter or the wax okay you need two
things to make a lamp you need cloth and
you need fuel okay
something has to make the cloth feed the
fire okay now what's the fire is your
awareness okay messed up awareness
samsara awareness okay
messed up state of mind that you were
born with defective from the factory
perception okay the light of perception
the light of awareness what you turn on
that formulas real number two okay that
light that comes from the so the lamp is
your awareness okay what feeds it the
cloth represents karma this is Kamala
Sheila the cloth the wick is karma the
oil or the wax is Wheel of Life link
number eight somebody tell me why I
drink this whole coffee that's how long
it's going to take yeah not bad I I
didn't even get to start okay
you want money right you want some money
you're low on money
somebody sends you some money through
robber s and gar okay from Guangzhou and
you have a choice you can pay taxes or
you cannot pay taxes you can report it
or you cannot report it okay nobody
knows about it okay somebody gives you
cash okay in return for a service late
in America you have to pay taxes okay
but you're thinking well nobody knows
about it I'll just spend the money you
know I'll just use the money I don't
have to pay taxes on it okay got it
so that attitude that desire wakes up
the karma scene okay
misunderstanding where money comes from
and the desire that comes from that
misunderstanding wakes up the Karma okay
what's the opposite of that in a good in
a good in a good scene what wakes it up
come on
coffee meditation okay rejoicing about a
good seed is the oil the good seed is
the wick got it in the case of a good
karma okay the wick is giving money to
someone else and the oil is dr. Chiba
making it mine making it mine I did that
I'm happy okay got it in this in in
Vaasa bondus understanding of this verse
deeper the lamp the third the third
example of the nine right the lamp the
wick is karma like being generous to
other people okay
giving money to other people the oil is
the coffee meditation having the right
attitude
I'm happy I did a good thing I'm happy I
did a good thing with those two you get
a fire okay and with a bad karma it's
the same okay
cheap your taxes cheat on your taxes
okay
that's the wick and the oil is I'm glad
I did the right thing
now I have more money this is the way to
make money okay got it you make it your
own
that's the oil okay without the oil the
Karma isn't very powerful okay you can
make a fire but it will burn out in one
minute right yeah it needs fuel fuel
this misunderstanding where money comes
from okay you okay you guys okay can I
go on okay ten downtown rhombus s let's
tie this - what's he always wanted to do
suffering he wasn't tired to suffering
okay he says the wick is the material
cause material costs okay what's a
material cause it's the thing that turns
into the other thing what's the material
cause for a tree the scene okay
the stuff in the scene becomes the stuff
in the tree and in Buddhism we call it a
material cause okay
direct costs the stuff in the seed
becomes the tree that's called material
cost okay and what's the contributing
cause water fertilizer sunlight okay
lack of Gophers
not exactly okay you okay so $10 Amba
wants to say there's a material cause
here is the wick the material cause of
the flame is the wick that contributing
cause is the oil okay
and they both represent suffering that
makes the fire of suffering okay then he
also heard Czech champions I was talking
to who wasn't to hear I think her
friends houses burned down this week in
California at four thousand houses six
thousand houses burned down and in
California these are not cheap houses
these are nice houses these people can
afford fire protection what happened I
said what happened you know
she said the wind went to fifty miles an
hour I've seen that kind of fire it
spreads from the top of the tree to the
top of the tree it doesn't even touch
the ground nobody can stop it that's
called chipper okay so understanding
numbered - okay if you have the material
cause of a bad karma if you have the
contributing cause of I'm happy I did it
it's called anti coffee meditation anti
coffee meditation are you sorry you did
that huh are you kidding I got more
money I would do it next week also if I
get a chance okay that bad attitude
about your bad Dean Chiba it tends to
multiply it tends to multiply okay so
for him we do this thing on some cup a
day we offer a thousand butter lamps you
know it takes about two months to make
the wigs by hand
with cotton balls in what you learn
quickly is you never put them all
together you spread them uh-huh okay if
you put them together they all join into
one big flame and they burn down the
house many Buddhist people have burned
down house it this way always spread
them out on the line okay otherwise they
all joined together into one huge flame
and you burnt down your house okay so
that's $10 rumpus understanding okay I'm
gonna stop there now I want to go over
your schedule for today and then we'll
stop oh I'm sorry oh I'm sorry I was I
thought it's 10 o'clock it's 10:30
let's keep going okay sorry to get your
hopes up sorry
we'll stop at 10:20 and talk about your
schedule okay we still have 20 minutes
is that okay with you okay
understanding number three about the
lamp
this is coin short-tempered during me
it's a little more difficult when we
talked about this star we talked about
the darkness the background darkness
which is emptiness okay and the light
which is all the stuff you ever
experienced the star okay to see the
star you need the background darkness
the background darkness in that way was
emptiness background emptiness okay only
if the world is empty can you see things
okay it's like only if you have a white
screen can you show a movie okay so you
need the screen background emptiness
okay in British terms numb tongue numb
tongue the emptiness which is the
background and then the appearance of
things coming from your karma okay that
was the star in the cataract we were
seeing things that couldn't be there
okay that was the relationship we saw
things that weren't really there okay
when he reaches this one which is the
lamp he says the emphasis here is none
none what appears to you okay what
appears to you people things okay the
light the lamp in this case is taken out
of the context of emptiness and treated
by itself you know why do I see things
why do I see people it's the process of
the silver seeds opening okay no no
reference to emptiness for quencher
10-bit do me okay because the word
appear in Tibetan is the same word for
lamp okay so what's the technical name
for that reality of the two kinds of
reality
deceptive reality okay why it tricks you
it fools you it looks like it's coming
this way to your mind to everything to
your eyes to your ears to your nose your
nose was defective from the factory okay
even your nose this oh look this guy
didn't take a shower today no you didn't
keep your sexual purity get used to it
no but he didn't take a shower with that
that's why he didn't take a shower okay
your nose reports that it's coming from
this guy it's not true it's coming from
you okay got it
if you were respecting other people's
relationships all the time everybody
around you would take a shower
do you understand okay so anyway for
quantity B term a third meaning of the
lamp is to emphasize the world that
seems to be coming this way Aria is the
name for people who saw emptiness
directly in the past okay
what's the name for people who are not
Aria or shortened total people who see
things coming this way oh my husband
yell at me I didn't do anything okay the
word for those people the word in
Buddhism for non ayah is incoming seer
okay incoming fear they see things
coming this way sort tongue okay sore
means this way tongue means see right
like tongue um so so tongue means this
is what the third meaning of the lamp is
okay people see things coming this way
got it can I go on all right
this is difficult but you like difficult
that's why you came to Diamond Mountain
this is Nagarjuna okay and quench your
timid this is the garnet and point you
tempered already things are empty but
they work things are empty but their
work in fact you can say I'm gonna kiss
you but your husband get mad and my
partner get upset at me okay things are
empty but they still work okay things
are empty but they still work okay
if the causes and conditions are there
they will work okay in in DCI this is
called the aspirin in DCI language this
is called the aspirin okay does Aspen
what's the function of aspirin take away
headache what's the thing inside the
aspirin called that takes away the
headache active ingredient no it's
called active ingredient okay it's
what's it called Connie cox-2 inhibitor
the chemical name is cox-2 inhibitor
okay it stops the nerve transmission of
pain okay the stuff in the aspirin this
stops your headache is called cox-2
inhibitor okay the active ingredient
okay trust me trust Carney she's you
didn't she's Canadian
okay
you can trust the communion now does it
work sometimes sometimes means it
doesn't work okay sometimes mean they
didn't find the real cause okay
sometimes mean it doesn't work okay you
will not get in a plane if it works
sometimes it falls down sometimes but
you will take an aspirin that works
sometimes it doesn't that's okay which
means the active ingredient is inactive
sometimes can we say that they should
call it the sometimes active ingredient
okay so when in Aspen works
what's the active ingredient yeah your
seeds your seeds because you helped
someone who had a headache last week
okay and you have seeds for the cox-2
inhibitor to stop your headings okay cuz
the cox-2 inhibitor isn't the active
ingredient your karma is the active
ingredient okay got it
that's all coins you tell me do mister
look you put together oil you put
together wick you put together fire it
will work but it's all coming from you
okay it's all coming from you it's empty
okay empty of what cox-2 inhibitor that
works okay got it
you okay you're awful quiet when you get
really quiet I think you're not
understanding okay okay okay
yeah it's your scenes that make the
aspirin work okay
it's your seeds that that make the
active ingredient active when it's
active because it ain't act
okay so is there a contradiction between
emptiness and a laugh no emptiness gives
the lamp a place to be okay
emptiness gives the lamp a place to be
emptiness means that the fire is not
burning on its own okay the fire is
burning because you have the Karma
there are slower schools of Buddhism
that say hot is part of fire heat is
part of fire wet is part of water the
higher school doesn't know who put the
hot in the fire
who put the wet in the water could you
remove the web from the water and walk
on the water if you had special
abilities no problem we believe those
stories are true Jesus walk on water we
say yeah he understood since he's talked
about seeds all day people say yes their
problem between Buddhism and
Christianity I say go away Jesus talk
about seed like all day give me a break
okay all right
that's all okay the sign that you
understand emptiness is that you are
more successful in your life okay
financially relationships health mental
state state of your world
okay these five things are coming from
you okay the sign that you understand
emptiness is that you can make things
happen okay got it
it's not this okay
what are you doing I'm a temp today um
that's a sign of person who doesn't
understand emptiness got it yeah all
right a person understands the emptiness
is like the person in the movie they're
excited in their life they can make
things happen they're having a fun life
things are going well okay because they
know how to plant seeds because they
understand things are empty got it
empty means they don't come from seeds
don't not come from since anyway you got
okay last one we got five or four I'm
sorry I'm sorry okay for now
coin tip dumpy Jimmy wants to make sure
you understand he kind of doesn't agree
with $10 Amba because he says don't
forget the good things also come from
causes the good things also come from
seeds okay in in British terms and in
Camilla Sheila terms and he's gonna talk
about it if we ever get there in the
scripture the causes for sansara and the
causes for nirvana
are the same the principle is the same
okay all the troubles in your life and
all the successes in your life are
coming from the same principle okay the
causes since oil wicks
fire okay that's number five okay the
good things and the bad things are
coming from your seats nope number four
was things still work even though
they're empty number five is good things
come from you and bad things come from
you okay and in British terms we would
always say corn day
corn day say corn day
horn Corman's cholera means sansara
cycle of life day means young and the
depa means nirvana they both come from
the same principles okay ultimate good
and ultimate evil come from the same
principles okay one day by the way the
correct pronunciation the pronunciation
is Sun Sara it's not Sam it's not Sam
before and ass sounds good mmm changes
to end Sun Sona
okay don't I don't want to hear anybody
say samsara I'm gonna choke you if you
say samsara then you'll see samsara okay
okay and it's not some big wheel of life
somewhere else okay tell me the moment
with the husband in the kitchen when you
give birth to son Sara no you're stupid
okay got it you replant again okay kids
are bad you call them stupid kids
you hear yourself you plant a sin next
week you come home your husband spent
husband says for no reason now your
husband says you're stupid
now at that point you can stop the blind
man or you can keep it going okay how do
you keep it going now you stupid okay
then the kids allowed to act up next
week got it that's called a mini sansara
so don't think son Cyrus is some big
rebirth bla bla okay you are making some
stars a hundred times a day okay your
reaction to problems is spinning the
wheel again and again and again now yes
stupid then I don't know why my kids act
up I don't know why my kids aren't
polite okay and my husband he called me
stupid for new easy no I think it's just
like this okay that sons are
okay the riddle Sansar and the root of
Nirvana are the same principle okay
the lamp deep deep oh okay
starter key me you guys gotta sing that
tomorrow okay get the pronunciation
right you might have to change a little
bit boot boot them swap them cha can you
sing it tomorrow that same tune
it's disgusting because it stays in your
head and then everybody will be able to
memorize the Sanskrit okay you listen to
these guys sing at one time you can't
forget it you want to forget it but you
can't okay it's good okay then we'll do
that after the meditation because if you
do it before the meditation
it ruins the meditation and then later
in the class someone's gonna sing a
Chinese version okay all right Stanley
not you no it's okay
can you find somebody teach us a nice
Chinese melody that will stay in the
head for the Chinese pronunciation okay
of the translation okay all right then
we can memorize this sounds good in the
Chinese okay all right I want to
memorize the Chinese how many we got
five okay number six this is easy
this one's from Geshe Michael there's a
famous metaphor in fact when they teach
us the word metaphor in the school they
always used life is a candle life is a
candle if you say life is like a candle
it's a simile if you say life is a
candle it's a metaphor so what's that
mean
it burns down okay trust me I'm watching
it okay it burns down every minute okay
that's impermanence okay so the last
meaning of the butter lamp is just
remember life is a candle okay life is a
candle every minute you are losing your
life it's a you are born with a debit
card and life costs you sixty five sees
a second okay
and it goes it's like a candle it's burn
burn burn burn burn then burn out okay
so that's pretty obvious but nobody
mentioned it okay so I threw in some of
those myself
we covered the three metaphor the first
three of the nine and they all relate to
how is the world around us okay how's
the world around us what's it like well
it's like a star it's like a cataract
and it's like a candle okay so we
finished the first big group of how many
well how many groups good now we're on
to the second group okay how many
members in the second group trick
question yeah only one what is it in
Sanskrit my say Maya Maya the root of
this word is not clear to anybody I
checked a lot of people nobody's really
sure it might be Maya which means to go
wrong it might be ma ma Kia which means
big power to to confuse you okay
like magnificent or Mahatma or
stuff like that okay it might be the
route I which means to go and sanskrit
like exit means go out it it is the past
tense of i okay so it might be ma eeeh
which means to go wrong okay anyway
nobody figured it out Maya means
illusion it has two big meanings in
Buddhism okay illusion can mean like you
think you see something but it's not
there okay and classically in the study
of perception illusion can have many
causes one is strong emotions when
you're angry or very jealous you see
things which are not there okay so
strong emotions what is called the
movement of things around you like if
you're at a stoplight with two cars on
either side and suddenly they both back
up at the same time you feel like you're
rolling into this into the intersection
you see it's an illusion of movement
okay if it happens once in a while right
both cars next to you they go back and
you feel like huh you slam on the brake
but actually you're not moving okay so
that's called adventitious illusion just
the way stuff is happening around you
confuses you or strong emotions okay
the second meaning of Maya in Buddhism
and by the way what was the Buddhist
mother's name Maya okay
the second meaning is magic trick and
we'll talk about it in I almost used a
magician pulling a rabbit out of a hat
okay in in the West in America the
illusion is when the guy goes like this
and he takes his hat and pulls a rabbit
or he he he takes a coin out of your ear
or something
like that it's called a magic trick okay
so Maya means either one when you drive
across the desert you see water far away
that's illusion or magician's trick Maya
can mean either one okay and I'm gonna
start it tomorrow okay I'll start it
tomorrow it's pretty obvious I'm gonna
give you nine meanings of the illusion
okay nine meanings all right it's your
history now let's talk about how are you
gonna meditate today what are you
supposed to do today besides sleep if
you have jet lag okay you're supposed to
go from here and you're supposed to make
yourself breakfast in your cottage
Veronica you're gonna make me a big
breakfast right okay then 11:45 to 12:15
you're supposed to relax
you cannot meditate if you haven't had
enough sleep forget it it's not gonna
happen
okay it cannot happen trust me I did 12
retreats and it doesn't work okay if you
feel like you need to sleep sleep okay
anytime today if you feel you need to
sleep sleep then get up and meditate
okay after you throw some cold water on
your head
but if you didn't sleep last night or
you have jet lag then sleep okay
personally if I have jet lag I have a
rule and every traveler frequent
traveler I have so many miles I'm off
the charts
recently the airline's sent me a
limousine to take me to the next
airplane at the next gate really okay so
every my advice frequent traveler if you
have jet lag don't go to sneem stay up
till nine o'clock at least nine o'clock
then you get back on schedule then you
can go home and get messed up again okay
but generally if you have not slept well
you have to sleep I've also found that
yoga's difficult if you haven't slept
okay you might want to sleep take
shavasana first and take another one
after incident right Scott right Scott
Scott's nickname is including shavasana
if we say we're doing an hour of yoga he
always says the same thing is that
inclusive lesson alright 12:15 goes
through these first three images okay go
through the star go through the cataract
and go through the lamp okay try to you
can keep a list of you know six words to
remind you if you have to peek with your
eye left is good luck okay you look like
a roadrunner right
kapnos it's a bird that lives around
here and they're going okay so you can
peek at your list six qualities okay
try to remember the meaning six meanings
okay and then try to think of something
real in your life okay the star which is
the illusion is my husband who hurt me
yesterday okay so don't every time you
do meditation
you should link it to your real life
okay don't make it some philosophy thing
okay think of people in your life who
are like stars think of times in your
life when you had cataracts okay got it
think of things that are empty but still
work like a limp like aspirin okay all
right five sorry yeah five fifteen take
a walk by the way me and Veronica are
gonna walk around and spy on you to see
if you're keeping a good retreat but
five fifteen go outside take a walk
enjoy the sunset hear a beautiful okay
wear a hat wear sunscreen so you don't
get big dots on your arms okay they
don't come on
four to five sorry both yeah okay both
you can also practice the first eight
levels or the llama but I suggest you do
it separately in the afternoon
don't try to do the whole lines dance in
one piece practice the first eight or
practice nine okay tomorrow we'll do the
first two parts of the Lions test their
five parts tomorrow we'll come back down
together okay tomorrow we'll come back
there today it was too long okay all
right so during the 12:15 to 1:30 or
during the fortifier if you want to warm
up with some lion that's fine just don't
growl okay 6:00 to 7:30 oh sorry
wear a hat wear sunscreen always take
water nobody walks in the desert without
water never ever okay I wear a little
bag over my shoulder then your hands are
free it's more fun okay mm keep a
building in sight okay I have got lost
walking around here I walked around for
five hours I couldn't find the houses
okay so it's and I lived here for seven
years
okay it's it can be dangerous okay so
keep a keep a structure inside okay all
right and don't get stuck out after dark
snakes like dusk because mice like dusk
why do mice like dusk it's hard for
snakes to see there
so they they all runner everybody's
running around at the same time just so
are you so be careful where you step
never step in the desert where you can't
see what's there
the only person who ever got been here
stepped over a log and there was a snake
on the other side and they didn't see
okay
so always look where you put your feet
okay if you get bit by a snake
sit down call somebody that's why we put
Internet here okay when you run around
the poison moves faster okay so relax
five-song okay and we'll take you to
hospital they give you an injection it's
all fine okay don't worry about it
if you hear a snake just don't look turn
around go the other way
some people like what's that they don't
want you to step on them they always
give you a warning this is it means I'm
here don't step on me they don't want
you to step you're too big to eat okay
they don't want to waste a poison on you
seriously they're not stupid if you step
on them they will get mad but otherwise
they they're very peaceful actually well
they have an attitude good nobody in the
desert bothers and snake except a human
okay I suggest you do lion again at six
before you do your comments you know
meditation okay and then 8:45 after
dinner
is a useless meditation time it's
hopeless so just do some light coffee
meditation gratitude meditation keep a
list to hell who helped you in your life
okay in your life many people helped you
starting with your mom and in your mind
thank them okay coffee big coffee
meditation
I like to drink hot chocolate I like to
sit in the most comfortable chair
forget meditation cushion I might sit on
the porch and watch the stars and also
mantra okay you can do your mantras I
used to lay down on the roof and do them
and watch the Stars and do mantras and
try to pick out satellites okay it's
kind of fun but I did millions of
mantras on the roof okay so take a chair
go outside and wear a sweater and enjoy
these beautiful stars okay you won't see
them anywhere almost anywhere in the
world we are very far from the city so
enjoy the Stars okay the main thing in
retreat is Fung song have fun don't get
all don't do yoga like this okay like
smile
I hate yoga okay same with meditation
don't try too hard okay the most common
mistake is people try too hard okay just
relax okay
okay you can't meditate if you're trying
too hard okay that's the main thing if
you're tired take a break okay all right